Hey everyone, welcome back to the
channel. I hope you guys are doing
extremely well. Just in case you're
about the first time over here, welcome
to the channel. And if you don't know
me, I go by the name Striver in the
programming community. If you want to
check me out, you can definitely check
me out on LinkedIn. I'll be leaving my
LinkedIn, Twitter, Instagram, Telegram,
all the social media handles in the
description below. So, without wasting
any time, let's get started. So, Take U
Forward is a full-fledged interview
preparation website that I run on my
end. So, if you're someone who has 3
months to like 6 months of time left for
interviews, I will definitely ask you
out to check this Striver's SD sheet.
Trust me, this is one of the most
followed resources in the country as of
now. What does this resource gives you?
It gives you
190 uh 191 well-curated problems such
that all your DS Algo concepts will be
covered. But, only prerequisite is you
should be well-versed with the basics of
DS Algo in order to start with.
Now, if you're someone who's a beginner,
you can definitely check out our
Striver's A2Z DSA course or sheet. Now,
over here what I've done is I've created
455 steps. Every step has been curated
properly, and you will get all the
problem links, everything. Imagine you
open dynamic programming, you want
video, you get videos for everything.
So, all the hard topics have been
covered. You'll find videos for all the
hard topics. Now, we will be starting
off to cover all the basic topics. So,
this is the video where we'll be
starting to cover from the step 1.1. In
case you have doubt about the
credibility, you can go to our LinkedIn
page, and you can check out all the
success stories. Or you can follow me on
LinkedIn, and you can see how many
people do tag me. And also, you can
check out our Instagram story
highlights. So if you go to Instagram,
there is a highlight as success stories.
Over there you can check out all our
success stories like there are thousands
and thousands of success stories of the
Striver's SD sheet. And now we are
starting off with Striver's A2Z DSA
course sheet, which is for beginners or
intermediate level people. Today we will
be covering the step 1.1, that is things
to know in C++ Java Python or any
language. Now in order to start off with
data structures and algorithms here to
pick up any one language. It can be C++
Java Python or JavaScript. And you have
to code in that language. Make sure you
master one language. Now
in the previous video I've already
talked about C++ versus Java, so you can
definitely check out that video. So in
this video I'll be telling you about C++
and I'll be covering all these basic
stuffs related to C++ and in the next
video we will be covering the Java one.
I think you should definitely check out
Coding Ninjas because
Coding Ninjas comes up with the best
curated and structured path of learning
and their courses may
The best thing about Coding Ninjas is
that they are like honestly Why do I
promote them? The reason is their
service. I feel like if you pay for
something you deserve that service and
that is where Coding Ninjas stand out.
Like their teaching assistant service
That gets resolved within 10 to 15
minutes.
You need someone who resolves your doubt
like within a second. And if you can't
believe it you can definitely check out
their Google reviews as well as Facebook
reviews. Content I think is good.
Content is top-notch. The service is
top-notch. If you want extra discount,
there's a link in the description. Make
sure you check them out. I'll be using
VS code in order to code. I'll be
writing my C++ code over here. I'll be
giving the input over here. And whatever
the code generates as an output will be
produced over here. So, before starting
this C++ video, I'd love to mention two
points. First is, please make sure you
watch the video till the end. You might
be knowing C++, but there are a lot of
things that I'll be covering in this
video which you might know or you might
like find it very interesting. So, make
sure you watch the video till the end.
The second point is again very
important. When you're learning
something on uh for the first time, do
not dig deep too much into uh certain
things because what happens is when we
start off, we start to think that,
"Okay, every certain thing we'll learn
in depth." And eventually, we are stuck
in the beginning process and we do not
move ahead. So, what I'll recommend you
is first learn the basics and do not dig
much. And eventually, when you'll uh go
from beginner to intermediate to medium
and then to hard, you will on this uh
flow, you will be learning everything in
depth. But during your start, do not dig
deep so much. Why? Why? Why? Do not do a
lot of why. It is good to do, but there
are certain things where you should not
do a lot of why's because that will be
not required in the longer run. So,
the first thing in order to write a C++
code is the skeleton of C++ code. Now,
the skeleton of C++ code stays constant
across all the programs that you'll be
writing in C++. Uh something like hash
include.
So, we write hash include. Now, imagine
the first program that we will be
writing is to print our name. So, the
skeleton states, "Okay, you have to
print you have to probably print
something which is you have to give an
output. Or let's say you have to take an
input. So in order to take an input or
take an output, we have to use this
particular library. Now, as I said, do
not dig deep. You don't have to know
what is inside this library. Yes, if you
want to know it is okay, but you don't
have to remember this. So if you use
this library, this allows you to take an
input and produce an output. And in
order to use this library in C++, we can
use the hash include. So hash include
iostream. Imagine if you want to use
something like a mathematical function
which exists in the C++ library, then
you have to use something like a math.h.
I'll be talking about mathematical
functions afterwards. In case you want
to use something like a string, then you
use hash include string. So whatever
library you want to use, you have to
hash include it. You don't need to know
what is inside the library. As I said,
do not dig much deep. And then you say
int main.
And then you say return zero. So this is
the generic skeleton of the code. I'll
remove this couple of hash includes
because as of now, we are just going to
print. So this is the generic skeleton
of a C++ code. After this I said, I'm
going to print my name. So I'll be like,
see out. So when I write see out, it
means you have to that allows you to
give an output. Okay. Now, in order to
use see out, you have to write std and
double colon. So see out is a function
which exists under the std. Okay, so you
have to say std, can you give me see out
and then two lower than signs and then
double quotes if you're printing a
string and you can say, "Hey Striver."
And then you can give this. So what I'll
do is I'll go and run this. The moment I
run this, you see in the output screen
we have, "Hey Striver." So in case you
want to again print this, so go across
and copy paste the same line and again
run this. So what happens is, "Hey
Striver" is printed two times, but
they're are printed on the same line. In
case you want to print them in different
lines, you can go ahead and give a
backslash n and you can just
So,
the moment you compile this, what
happens is the backslash n goes across
and prints it in the new line. So, very
simple. Can Can we use something else?
Yes. Instead of a backslash n, we can
take std and l and we can again compile.
So, if we compile, endl is similar to
backslash n. Endl or backslash n takes
you to the next line, but usually people
use backslash n because it is faster.
Okay, but you will find people using
both, so it is your choice. If you want
to print something on the same line, you
can again print
something like Hey Raj. You can again
print and again you can give something
like endl. There is no limitations on
the thing that you want to print on the
same line. You can print as many things
over here on the see out and that will
be printed according to the functions
that you give. Like over here given
endl, so that is why Hey Raj, Hey Raj
and Hey Raj and Hey Raj and Hey Raj are
printed on new lines. So, this is how
you give. Now, something must be very
annoying, which is this std. Now, for
any functions, for most of the functions
you have to write std double colon
double colon. This is very annoying,
right? This is where something like
using namespace comes in. So, we say,
"Hey, can you use the namespace std?"
So, basically what this means is if
you're not giving anything, if you're
not stating anything, it eventually
says, "Since you have written using
namespace std." Again, you don't have to
dig deep. The moment you say this, the
program always uses std for all the
functions. Yes, always uses std for all
the functions. Now, if you compile, it
prints everything. Now, it looks a
easier task, isn't it? So, this is how
you can easily write Okay. Now, let's
quickly have an input. Imagine you want
to take an input. So, imagine I want to
take an integer as an input. int x. So,
this is how you take
an input. It's a cin of x. cin means
input into this variable. Input into
this variable. Now, imagine in the
input, I go across and I say 10. And
I'll be like, let's print this x guy.
So, I'll be like, value of x. And then I
can go ahead and write x. If I go and
print this, you will see value of x is
printed as 10. What happened? You
printed this particular string, and then
you said space, and then you printed x.
So, this x was taken from here. Got it?
Imagine if you want to take two
variables as input. So, if you want to
take two variables as input, you can
give it like this. And over here, you
can give them in the same line. The
value of x
And then you can go ahead and say, and
y. And you can probably write this as
that
this one and this. So, what happens is
value of x and y. Now, do you need to
give them in the same line? You can give
them in different lines as well, and it
will still run in the similar fashion.
So, this is how you can take any inputs.
So, what happens is the first thing gets
into the first cin. The next thing gets
into the next cin. So, depending on how
you are writing cin, line by line, line
by line, everything gets into variables
that you're initializing it with. Now,
you might be thinking, what is this end?
Now, there are certain things as data
types, which I'll be talking about. But
before moving into data types, now as I
said, there are a bunch of libraries.
Imagine you're taking string, integer,
let's say a lot of other data types, or
a lot of other libraries. Will you be
writing hash include, hash include, hash
include, hash include every time? No,
it's going to take you a lot of time.
This is where C++ says, "Hey, I've got
something better for you." I say, "Can I
write bits/stdc++.h?"
Now, what it does is it includes all the
libraries, everything.
Whatever libraries are there in C++,
everything is included under this
bits/stdc++.h.
You might think, "But Striver, in order
to include so many libraries, we will be
taking a lot of time." Yes, we do take a
lot of time, but that is very negligible
compared to the time that your program
takes to run. So, that is why it is okay
to include bits/stdc++.h.
Yeah, it takes a bit more time, but that
is okay. Again, if you want to check out
what are the libraries inside this, you
can definitely Google this, and you'll
get all the list of libraries that are
inside this particular directory. So,
this is
what is
the common skeleton of the code that we
will be using to write any C++ program
on the planet. So, we have discussed the
first thing, that is the skeleton of the
code, and the user input and output to a
certain extent. We will be digging deep
into this as we move forward. What is
the next type? That is the data types.
Now, we're talking about input and
output. Now, if you're taking a number
in, you have to store it somewhere in
your program. That is
the the place where you store, that can
be a data type. Okay. Now, imagine
you're taking a number like 10, 12, -5.
What will you use to store it? So, there
is a data type known as int, integer.
Now, this is how you can write comments
in C++ if you give double backslash, you
can write any comment. So, integer, what
this comment means, those lines of
code will not be executed. So, this line
will not be executed when the program is
executed.
So, int is the data type. In order to
assign anything to integer data type,
you have to write the data type and then
a variable name. Variable name can be
anything. It can be Raj, it can be X, it
cannot be a number. It cannot be a
number. Okay. So, it can be Raj1. That
is okay. But, it has to be something
which has a character. So, something
like let's say I say X equal to 10. So,
this is how you assign something
into an integer data type. But, integer
has certain restrictions. It can only
store numbers from this range to this
range. Beyond this, it cannot store.
Beyond this, what will help you?
Something like a long data type will
help you. If you try to use long, it has
a wider range. Same concept, you can use
the same concept to store
uh variables in long. If you want to
take an input, this is how you take an
input. If you write seen of X, the first
number 10 will go into X.
Okay. Now, what if you want to store
bigger numbers than this? This is where
something like long long will come in.
So, if you're saying long long, it will
give you a wider range. Again, the same
way, you can store it like this or maybe
you can go ahead and store
a very large number as well. So,
usually, we will be using these three
things to store any type of integers
between a certain ranges. Okay. Now,
what are the next data types that we
will be using? We were talking about
integers. What if we have something like
let's say 5.6, something like this. So,
it is having something after the decimal
point. This is where something like
we will be specifically using two data
types, float and double. Again, they
have ranges. Depending on the range that
you use, you'll be using float or
double. The ranges are visible on the
screen. So,
we can use something like
float. Again, same way.
Float X equal to 5.6. Again, you can
always store float Y equal to 5 as well.
It doesn't mean that like if I'm saying
that it has to store decimal, it doesn't
mean you can store an integer. If you go
and say see out of y
like value of y and then you say, "Okay,
let's print this one. Let's see what it
prints, okay?"
So, if you see the value of Okay, it
does give you an error. Okay, by the
way, let's erase this because we have
defined x twice. Okay, let's now compile
this. You see, it is getting printed.
Similarly, if you want to define this as
double,
it says still okay.
If we define this double, an integer can
also be stored in a double, okay? So, in
data types, you have learned how to
store numbers and numbers with decimal
points. Now, what if you have a string
or a character? How do you store that?
So, for that, what we will be using is
something like a string and get line.
So, you have to learn these couple of
things, okay? Now,
imagine I write hey striver.
So, this is an entire string and the
same way I'll say string s and I'll say
cn of s. I'll say c out of s.
Okay. Ideally, what should happen is
this entire hey striver should go inside
this string and this should be printed.
But, let's see what will happen. If I
run this,
you will see just hey being picked up.
And if you want to pick up striver, what
you have to do is you have to define two
strings. If you want to define two
strings in a same line, comma will be
the thing or you can go ahead and say
string s2 and over here s1 and then you
can say s2 and over here s1 and then you
can give a space and then s2. So, what
will happen?
Now, if you do, first s1 is picked up as
hey, then s2 is picked up as striver,
then both of them are printed with a
space.
Right. So,
if you're saying string, then what
happens is it only picks up anything
before the space.
And after the space, it's a new string.
So, you have to again give a C in. Now,
in case you want to take everything
together in a string, how do you do
that? In order to do that, you have to
probably define a string.
And then you have to use something like
get line. Inside the get line, you have
to write C in. What is get line again?
Do not need to dig deep. It's an
internal function. You have to write C
in.
And then you have to give this variable
over here.
And then you go ahead and say C out of
STR. So, what will happen is this get
line will take the entire line and put
it into the STR. And now if you print,
you will see this hey driver is printed
or maybe hey driver, I am school.
And if you print this, you will see the
entire line is getting printed. But if
you go to the next line, hey Raj, will
the entire line be picked up? Let's run
this. No, the next line is not picked
up. Only this particular line is picked
up. So, the moment you click enter, the
next line will not be picked picked up.
So, it just picks up till the line
break. So, string and get line is used
to take any of the string.
So, you have talked about string and get
line. Now, it's time to talk about
character. Now, there are 256 characters
in English dictionary. So, character can
store all of them. Yes, character can
store all of them. So, imagine if you
have something like an H. So, you can
just go ahead and declare char CH. And
you can take C in of CH. Okay? And then
you can say C out of CH. So, what will
happen is this H will go inside this and
it will be printed over here. If you
want to declare a character, you can go
ahead and declare this as G. So, single
quotes is what will be used to declare a
character.
You can also declare it as string, but
usually string will be within double
quotes. That is also okay. But string
ends up taking uh much more space. That
is why if it's a single character, we
tend to use something like a cat. So,
okay, do we have Okay, so these are the
data types that I have used till now to
solve all the problems in DS algo. Did I
require anything else? No. In case I've
required for a single problem like one
problem here or there, I have done a
Google search and I've used that, but I
can assure you that if you know this,
that is more than enough. Now, you must
be having a lot of questions. So, if we
have something like a 10, and that 10
can be stored in all the three or all
the five,
why can't we use simply long long or
maybe double? Now, the thing is
everything takes up a certain space in
your uh computer. Now, you can't be like
you can you can't use long long to store
10. That will not make sense because it
will end up eating up a lot more memory
space. So, integer takes a certain
memory, long
does take a certain memory. So,
everything will take a certain memory.
So, depending on that, we decide what to
use. Now, integer has a range. Now,
those numbers you can't uh remember. So,
what I usually do is I keep a rounding
off number. Like I know integer will be
from -10^9
to 10^9, like rounding off. Long will be
-10^12
to 10^12. Long long will be -10^18 to
10^18. So, whenever there is something
as 10^13, I switch to long long. Don't
have to remember exact exact numbers
because you will not remember that much
when you go on the longer run. Okay, so
that is how I usually do it, and you can
also follow the same process. So, we
have completed data types. Now, the data
types that I've covered that are more
than enough. Again, very crucial point.
Do not do not dig deep because
eventually, when you keep on coding,
you'll learn everything. Okay? First, uh
third thing, if else statements. Let's
go. So, till now we know the skeleton of
the code. We know the data types. Now,
let's write some program. So, the first
program is write a program that takes an
input of a age and prints if you are an
adult or not. So, the skeleton is
something which I've written and this is
the program. So, let's break down the
problem. It states write a program.
Maybe I've written the skeleton.
That takes an input of age. Now, you
know one thing. Age will be
what? An integer? 18 or maybe double.
Imagine the age we are talking in terms
of integer. And we know you're called an
adult when you're greater than 18.
Correct? So, imagine I enter something
like 19. In that case, you have to print
adult. Imagine I enter something like
17. You have to say not an adult. We
have print 18.
Uh adult. Right? If I print 10, not an
adult. So, I need an age. So, maybe I
can go ahead and say, "Okay, I need
age."
So, you need the age from the user. So,
see in
Hey, give me the age. So, maybe if I
give the age over here
or something like this, this will be
picked up into this age. Now, this is
where something like if else statement
comes in. What is it saying? Print if
you're adult or not. Can I say
if you are greater than equal to 18,
then I can say you are an adult. You are
an adult. Yes. Or if you are lesser than
18, you are not an adult. Can I say
this? So, this is something which you
are speaking in very layman terms. If
you want to convert this into
programming language, this is where
something like if else comes in. There
is something as if.
This is the block. And there is
something like else. This is the block.
So, inside this, you perform stating,
"Okay,
if something happens, perform these
lines of code. If that thing doesn't
happens, go and perform these lines of
Okay? So, I'm saying if
the age is greater than or to 18, then
go and perform this. And if it is not,
go and perform this else. Very simple.
And if I'm saying if the age is greater
than 18, what am I doing? I'm saying
print you're an adult. So, the print
line is very simple.
You are an adult. Simple.
Like you can just capitalize this. And
if you are not, then go ahead go ahead
and print this.
You are not an adult.
So, basically first line says 20 will go
on to age, then it will say 20 greater
than equal to 18, yes.
It will go
inside this and print this. So, let's
run this and see what happens. So, I'm
taking 20, yes, you are an adult. If I
take 15, what will happen? It will say
you are not an adult. Simple. Now, this
is the basic if else statement. Now, you
can modify this as well. Now, imagine
you are saying
for an example, you are saying
18, yes, 18, no.
I can also write this
as this. This is okay. This is saying
age is greater than equal to 18. If not,
go to the else. But only get into the
else if the condition satisfied. Over
here, it will, but eventually you will
learn. Is it mandatory to write an else
statement always? You can omit the else
statement as well. So, if you omit the
else statement, what will happen is
the 15 will be taken as the input and
the if will not be executed and it will
not find an else. So, nothing to be
executed, complete it. So, it is not
mandatory to have an else statement. If
you're having a if, it is not mandatory
to have a else statement. So, coming
back to the else if, what happens if
you're giving 15? The if is false, it
states
no, not greater than equal to 18. So, go
to the else, but else says, wait, before
going into me, you have to pass my
condition. My condition states, are you
lesser than 18? And it says, yes, I'm
lesser than 18, so I will go. If this
was lesser than 10, see what will
happen. You're giving 15, I'm taking 15,
false.
Goes to else.
And else condition says lesser than 10.
When I run,
it doesn't runs. Why? False. Again
false. No execution. But the moment you
give something as nine, see what will
happen.
When you give it nine, it prints Y. Goes
here, false.
Goes to the else, and he says, nine
lesser than 10? Yes. Goes ahead and
prints this. This is how something like
a if and an else if block works. Got it?
So let's now move on to a complex
problem so that you can understand the
conditional statements in depth. So this
is how you can write the multi-line
comments. Since I had an entire problem
statement, I put them under multi-line
comment. So
backslash asterisk is how you can do it.
For single-line, it is very simple,
double backslash. But front slash or
backslash, whatever you call it call it.
So this is how you can write the
multi-line comment. So the problem is
very simple. A school has following
rules for grading system. Below 25,
grade F. 25 to 44, grade D. 45 to 49,
grade D and so on. So your task is to
ask user to enter marks and print the
corresponding grade. Okay. So what is
the first stating?
Get the marks. So imagine
I have to take the marks. So this is how
I'll take the marks. This is something
which we know. What is the next line?
Below 25, very very importantly, below
25. So I'm saying, if the marks are
below 25, can I say the grade is for
sure That is something which I
definitely know. If the marks are below
25, I know the grade is F. If the mark
is between this,
can I write if the marks Now over here
there are two conditions.
Should be from 25 and should be till 44.
So, can I say should be greater than 25
and and if you have multiple conditions,
if you want to satisfy multiple
conditions, you say and and marks lesser
than equal to 44. This is how you
satisfy multiple first condition and and
second condition.
And then you say see out E. Similarly,
you can go ahead and write all the if
conditions. So, what I've done is I've
written all the conditions. You see, all
the conditions are written. Let's take
uh the marks as 85 and see which
condition is getting executed. So, if
you take the marks as 85, this is
executed. If you take something like 24,
let's see what is executed. You see,
everything is running fine. But, is this
the correct way to write? No. Why? What
happens is the marks is going and
checking this if.
Imagine the marks is something like 86.
This if is false. Again, goes and checks
this. False. Again, goes and checks
this. False. Again, goes and checks it.
False. Again, goes and checks this.
False. So, at the end this is executed
and A is printed over here. Okay. Now,
imagine if I give 24.
What will happen?
F will be printed, right?
So, this is executed. True, prints it.
But, then goes ahead, this is executed
false. This is executed false. Executed
false. Executed false. Executed false.
Only this was true. But, all the ifs got
executed.
Hence, you ended up taking a lot of
time. This is where Yes, this is where
something like an else if comes in. So,
if you write else if, see what happens.
Else if.
You can write else if. You can write
else if. You can write else if. So, if
you write else if, what will happen is
if 24 is true over here, none of these
lines will be executed because it states
else, it will never go there and it will
not be executed. So, you'll be saving a
lot of time.
Previously, in every if was executed.
So, this is why else if will be written.
Now,
another thing.
You're having 24. Imagine if you have
something like let's say
30.
So, you're saying if
not lesser than 20. So, this is false.
This is definitely false.
Do you need to check again for greater
than equal to 25? Because you are sure
that it is not lesser than 25. You are
sure because this is false. You are sure
that it will definitely go here. So, you
don't need to write this anymore.
You don't need to write this anymore
because if it is lesser than 25
and if it is lesser than equal to 44,
that means it is between 25 to 44. It
means that. And if this is also false,
that means it is not lesser than equal
to 44. You can also omit this.
See, you can also omit this.
Same way because 49 is checked, 59 is
checked, so you can omit checking
greater than 60 and eventually you can
do this. So, you saw how easily I
trimmed it down.
This is how you will be trimming it
down. So, if I now feel, you see 30 is
printing E. If you give something like
40,
that will be printing D. So, every line
is executed properly because if all
these are false, which means the number
is never lesser than 49. And if it is
true, it means 50 to 59. Super simple.
Got it? This is how you trim down
multiple conditional statements and
multiple if statements. So, this is the
last question for conditional statements
and over here we will be learning
something about nested if else. So,
Well, problem is pretty simple.
Take the age from the user and then
decide accordingly. So, if the age is
smaller than 18, you can print this and
all the conditions are given to you. So,
something we know for sure is we need
age, right? So, we can take the scene of
age. Now, we know something if age is
smaller than 18, then we got to print
something like not eligible
for job, right? This is what we will be
printing, correct? Then it states else
if the age is greater than equal to 18,
you will be printing eligible for job.
If it is greater than equal to 18,
you'll be printing eligible for job.
Okay, but if it is somewhere between
this, which means anywhere between
this,
it's eligible for job. But anywhere
between 55 and 57, eligible for the job,
but retirement soon. That is what you
have to print. Got it? So, what I will
go ahead and do is I'll say okay, else
if age is greater than 18 and and age is
lesser than equal to 54. And you can say
see out eligible for the job. So, I'll
just copy paste this and print.
Perfect. Again, do you need to write
greater than 18? No, because if this is
false, it is definitely greater than
equal to 18, so let's remove.
Simple.
What else?
If
if these two are false, that means it's
not lesser than equal to 54.
So, you just need to check if it is
lesser than 57.
If it is lesser than 57, you go ahead
and print see out
of
this statement.
Very simple. You go ahead and print this
statement.
Super simple. And if it is not less than
equal to 57, it's greater. And if it is
greater, it will always go to else. It
will always go to else. And if it is
going always to else, you can always say
see out
retirement time. Very simple. This is
how you can easily write it. So, if else
if else if and the last can be written
you can write the conditional of greater
than 57 or you can just leave it as it
is. So, imagine I give you something
like 55. Let's see if it is working
fine.
55 says eligible for job but retirement
soon. Now,
if I want to convert this into an S data
just to explain you an S data. Something
to
figure out. So, over here it states
18 to 54 is eligible for job.
Even 55 to 57 is eligible for the job.
But retirement is soon. That's the extra
addition that I have to tell the user.
Just retirement is soon as what I have
to tell the user. So, can I write
something like this? Hey, wait.
Can I write 57?
And can I omit this? So, if I omit this,
what will happen?
For everything less than equal to 57
and greater than 80
I'll always say eligible for job.
Inside this, can I say
if
if the age is greater than 55 because I
know if it is coming inside, it's
greater than 18. That is something I
surely know it's greater than 18 and
less than 57. If it is going inside
these blocks, and it will definitely
print eligible because I know for
everyone from 18 to 57, they're
eligible. But if the age by chance
exceeds 55, and I know it will always be
less than 57,
then only I go ahead and say, "Hey, if
it is exceeding, then can you go ahead
and say
retirement soon, but retirement soon."
That is the extra thing that you need to
print, right? But retirement soon. So,
this is how you can also write it. So,
this is what you call as nested if. So,
what happened was you just took out the
if from here and you put it over here.
Does it save time? No. I just wanted to
tell you that inside if inside else if
you can also write conditional. Inside
this if you can go ahead and write
another conditional. So, it can go
nested. These are called nested if else
statements. Inside if one if, so nested
ifs. Got it? So, you can write
conditions according to your choice and
eventually when you go across time and
you solve tougher problems you'll see
that you'll be writing multiple such
conditions. Okay. So, we have completed
the if else statements now. What's the
next thing? We'll be completing the
switch statement. We are talking about
switch statement, so we will be taking
this problem in order to understand the
switch. It is similar to if else. We
generally don't use switch that much,
but it is handy to know the switch
statements as well. So, what is the
problem stating? Take the day number and
print the corresponding day. For one, if
they're giving the day number as one you
have to print Monday. For two, you have
to print Tuesday and so on. For seven,
you have to print Sunday. So, they'll be
giving you a number between one and
seven. So, the syntax of switch is super
simple. So, you take the let's say the
number the day number.
Same day. So, whatever variable you're
taking
on that you have to write the switch.
It's kind of a switch. So, you say
switch day.
Okay? And then you open the braces. So,
on the basis of the day
you the switch will be triggered. Okay.
So, you know the switch will be between
one to seven because they're saying the
input will always be between one to
seven. So, you write case one.
Okay? So, case and then if this is an
integer you write the integer. If this
was a character then you could have
write uh written a character like this.
Whatever is your switch, you write the
same switch over here. So, case one is
the switch.
And then you go ahead to write case two
is the switch. And then you go ahead to
write case three is a switch and so on.
So what I've done is
So what I've done is I've written down
all the cases because those are the
cases. Now, I know one thing, for case
one, I have to print what? I have to
print see out of nothing but Monday. So
go ahead and print Monday. Similarly,
Tuesday, Wednesday, please print out
everything.
So this is how you'll write down all the
cases. In order to understand switch
better, let me give you an example.
Imagine you enter five. So what will
happen is it will take the input as
five. Switch says five. It will directly
go to case five and print Friday. But
see what happens.
It prints Friday, Saturday.
So it went to the case five
and it executed all the corresponding
cases.
But it started from case five. Imagine
you give two.
It will start from case two and it will
execute everything. So how do you
prevent this? Something for sure is when
you trigger two, it reaches here. It
doesn't execute this. So once it reaches
here, there is something as break
statement in C++. What break does is it
breaks out of all the conditional
statements that you have written. So
over here, the cases are conditional
statements. It will break out. The
switch is a conditional statement. So it
will break out. See what will happen. If
you give a break everywhere. So make
sure you give a break everywhere after
every condition.
If you give a break after every
condition and after all the cases are
executed and if I just give a see out to
check, see what will happen. And I'll
also give a see out to check after all
the cases have been executed. Okay,
check inside switch. So ideally what
should happen is two means Tuesday
should be executed. Break means all the
cases, and as as I said, all the
condition, this will also be broken out
and it will reach the line number 36.
See. So, if I give it, it reaches the
line number 36 check and not over here.
Very important to understand this. Okay.
Now, there is something as a default.
Imagine I give you something like
19. Then, what happens? So, if I
execute, if I give 19,
none of the cases gets executed because
there is no case as 19.
So, you you can probably give something
as a default case.
Imagine none of the cases is executed,
then it falls back on the default. So,
if you give something like as 19, it
falls back on the default and you can
say as invalid. So, this is the last
executed step. They don't need to give a
break because after this, it
automatically breaks out. So, imagine
you give you if you give 19, what will
happen is it will go ahead and say
invalid and then go over here. If you
don't give a break here, and if you give
something like see out invalid check.
Can you guess what will happen?
Because you're not giving a break.
See what happen.
Invalid and then the last line of the
switch is also executed. But, the moment
you write break,
it breaks out. It doesn't execute this.
So, whenever you write break, it will
take you out
from all the conditional loops or all
the conditional braces that it has above
it. Got it?
By the way, we will be using break a lot
of times in the upcoming problems. So,
uh your concept about break will get
more and more clear as we will be
solving problems in the upcoming
lectures. So, this was about the switch
statement. It is kind of similar to if
else. So, that is why people tend to use
if else because that is more readable.
But, yeah, it is handy to know switch.
So, just uh just in order to know, just
know it.
So, we are done with the switch
statement. Now, we will be knowing the
basics of arrays and strings. Now,
arrays will be covered in depth. Over
here, we'll be covering 41 problems and
strings will be covered uh on the
upcoming lectures, but as of now, we
just need to know the basics of arrays
and strings. So, let's uh start with
arrays and strings.
So, when do we use arrays is a very big
question. When you have a similar data
type being stored multiple times. For an
example, over here, I'm giving you four
uh datas. So, you can see that uh these
are integer data types, right? 3 4 5 7,
these are integers. So, one of the ways
you can store them is by the way,
template, yeah. One of the ways you can
store them is a b c d and you can say c
in of a, a will take three. Then you can
say b, b will take four, c will take
five, and then d. So, actually, all
these four integers, one by one will go
into these four variables. But imagine
if you have 50 variable uh 50 data, you
can't have 50 variable names because to
name 50 variables, it's going to take a
lot of effort. That is where something
like an array is used. So, what I say
is, I know the entire data is of similar
type, which is integer. Why can't I
define an array? So, what I do is I say
I N T array of, let's uh for an example,
say five numbers are there. I N T array
of five. So, what this does is, I'll
give you a diagrammatic representation.
This creates an array of size
five.
Now, this size five array looks
something like boxes. Every box can
store an integer. The zeroth index can
store an integer. The first index can
store an integer. The second index can
store an integer. And all the index can
store an integer. What is an index? This
first guy is referenced by zeroth index.
The second guy is referenced by first
index, one less. So, if the size is
five, the last index will be four. So,
this is how an array will look. And
depending on the data type that you have
given, every box or every location of
that array or that index is going to
store an integer. If you would have
defined it as, let's say, long long, it
would have stored long long in that
index. If you would have defined it as
character, it would have stored
character in that index. So, over here,
our use case is defining it as an
integer. So, I will define it as an
integer. Now, I'll say seen of array of
zero, seen of array of one,
seen of Oh, my bad. I'm taking the other
one. Array of two. Then I'll say array
of three. Then I say array of four. So,
what happens is the zeroth index takes
three and everything is stored. Now,
imagine I want to print seven. I want to
print seven. So, what you can say is see
out of array of
Where is seven stored? Seven will be
stored at the zeroth zeroth index, first
index, second index, third index. I can
say three.
Yes. And if you print this, let's see if
seven was stored. You saw? So, what
happened was these five numbers went in
and were stored in these places
consecutively. So, when you access the
third index, it means the fourth element
got accessed and you got the fourth
element. Can you modify these? Yes, you
can. If you want to do operations on
them, you can. Imagine I say array of
three. Can you go ahead and add yourself
10? So, if it adds 10 to itself, seven
should become 70. Let's see if it
become.
It does. So, you can modify. So, it is
exactly as a data type. You Like
whatever you wish to do, you can do it.
If you want to do something like, "Hey,
array of three, replace yourself with
16. Change your value to 16." It can as
well. You can do whatever you wish to
with this particular
array. You can treat it similarly to an
integer data type. Got it? So, this is
how you can store similar data like
together. And the container used is
array. There are multiple other
containers as well. I have talked about
that in the C++ STL video. You can
definitely check it out as well. So, we
got to know what is an array. And the
most important thing is everything has
to be of a similar data type. You can't
be saying 7.7.
If you say 7.7, what will happen is
since you declared this to be an integer
data type, this 7.7 will trim itself to
an integer and hence it will be stored
as seven. Got it?
If there is a double data type, maybe
you can store double. And if you say
double, then 7.7 is stored. Whatever
data type you give, that has to be
constant for all the elements. That is
the key point. Okay. So, that was about
the array. Now, where is the array
stored? We know it is zero at the next
first index. But, the entire thing is
taken and stored in a memory location.
Yes, the entire thing is taken and
stored in a memory location. So, this
guy, zero at index, is stored at a
particular memory. And that memory at
can be of any address. That address is
very random. I cannot say that it is
stored in let's say India. Like, there's
nothing like at this memory address it
is stored.
Throughout the CPU, it can be stored
anywhere.
Now, the second, the first index.
Now, that one I can definitely say will
be stored right after the zero at guy.
Right after the zero at guy's memory
address. Right the consecutive one. Then
the first the second guy will be stored
right after that. So, the zero at guy,
we're not sure. But, we are sure about
the next guys because they will always
be in
consecutive.
So remember, array elements are stored
in consecutive memory address, but I'm
not sure where the first one will It can
be at any
randomized location. Very, very
important point to remember, but will it
be required in DSL go? I don't think so.
But it is a point which is important and
you should keep in your mind. So till
now we did learn about the one D array.
Now we will be learning about the 2D
array. What is a 2D array? Again, I'll
be giving you very basic idea about 2D
array over here. Eventually, when we
move across the playlist, we will be
learning about 2D array in depth.
If this was declared,
this was something like
five
guys or five boxes.
Indexing from 0 1 2 3 4. Correct? Now,
the moment I say
I need five boxes, but I need them three
times.
I'll add three.
What it means is I'll have three five
boxes. If I show you diagrammatically,
this is what I'll have. Three 1 2 3 five
boxes 1 2 3 4 three five boxes as what
I'll have. So this is what it means.
This is the row number. We generally
call this as row
and this is column.
And if I talk about the indexing over
here,
again, the indexing starts from zero.
And this is how the indexing goes. You
see zero
1 2 and this is zero.
So this guy
this guy is known as 0 0.
This guy is known as 0 1. This guy is
known as 0 2. This guy is known as 0 3.
So this is how the naming or the row and
column goes. If I say 1  3, so
here is 1 and here is 3. 76. The value
will be 76. If I say give me the value
at 1, 3, the value will be 76. Again, if
you want to assign, like it'll be like
A13 equal to you can say 78, and then
you can go ahead and say C out of A13.
We will be seeing the use of 2D matrix a
lot. We'll be solving a bunch of
problems. Don't worry about that. So,
this will be array, and this will be
array. So, if you go ahead and print
this, you'll be seeing that we actually
getting 78 at this location. And for the
locations that you have not defined,
they'll be assigning themselves some
garbage value. It can be any value. Like
if you try to define
try to print print 1, 2, you'll see it
is having a garbage value. Like if you
try to print it again, it will have
different different values. Every time
you print, it has some garbage value
that comes in from the system because
you did not initialize. The only guy
that you initialized one was the first
row and the
third column in terms of zero-based
indexing. Very important. In arrays, we
have zero-based indexing. Okay? Where is
2D array used? It is used to solve a lot
of matrix problems, a lot of graph
problems, which you'll be dealing with
in the future. Okay? As of now, just
know this is what we know as 2D array.
This is the row. This is the column, and
it goes as row and column. That's it.
That is what you have to keep in your
head as of now.
So, in the STL video, I've talked about
a lot of functions related to arrays,
vectors, lists, and a lot of other
things. So, you can definitely check the
check that video after this one. So, we
have known about arrays in basics. Now,
let's talk about string. So, imagine
this is the string that I'm having.
String S equal to string.
And now,
I want to access I.
So, the string also stores every
character in terms of indexes.
So, S will be at the zeroth index. So,
if If try to print something like C out
of S of zero, what will happen? See.
S will be printed. If you say S of one,
see what happens. T will be printed. If
you say S of two,
you know what will be printed. R. So,
every
character is stored at an index. And the
first index is the zeroth index. And
what will be the last index? Whatever is
the length. So, can I say the length is
This is how you find the length. Length
equal to S.size. Or there is another
function as length which you can use.
So, if I say length minus one, because I
know last index, because everything
works in zero-based indexing. The last
index will be n minus I know it. If I
print this,
what will be printed? Driver R. Because
this is what happens at the last index.
That's how you can easily access the
string. If you want to change any value,
imagine you want to say, "Hey, I'm not
interested in this.
Please make it Z." S.try Z.
And I do it. It gets changed to Z. So,
you can also change it. Remember, these
are characters. Characters at every
index.
And characters when gets added makes up
a string. So, all of these are
characters. You can't do something like
this and expect this to work. If you do
this, it will not work and it will give
you errors. You see errors. So, since it
is a character, you have to assign it
with a character. So, string is storing
characters within itself. So, if you
know about this and the length function,
eventually we will be solving a lot of
string problems. And there you can
easily get on with strings. So, we are
done with arrays and strings. Now, it's
time to do for loops and while loops.
And as of now, I'll be talking about
basics. Eventually, we'll be solving a
bunch of patterns. A bunch of patterns.
And once you end up solving all these
patterns using for loops, trust me, your
logical thinking, your concept of for
loops will be super strong. And then
we'll move on to solving maths and
everything using the for loops and while
loops. And eventually, in the entire
DSA, for loops
If you don't know for loops, you can't
do anything. So, please stay focused.
So, what is for loops? Why is it used?
Imagine I say you, "Hey, print your
name."
I'll be like, "Uh see out." Okay, what's
my
My name is Priyo.
And I'll print it.
Print it five times.
Done.
Five times printed.
Print it 500 times. 500?
That's a lot.
This is where for loop comes. For loop
says,
"Same line of code.
Why do you want to write it again and
again? I'll do it for you."
So, what for loop says is, "Hey,
same line of code, right? Write it once.
And then enclose it
inside me enclose it."
And the for loop says, "Okay, my syntax
is very simple. Say for
What is the variable that you want to go
across? How many times you want to run?
Put over variable for that." I'll be
like, "I'm going to run it for five
times or 500 times."
What is the initial?
First, I equal to one. Variable
declaration, I equal to one. Variable
declaration. This only gets executed for
the first iteration. Only gets executed
for the first iteration. Then,
condition at which I'll stop. The for
loop will stop. The looping will stop.
So, I'll be like, the condition is 10.
I'm saying,
"Till I don't reach 10, I'll not stop.
And at every step, I have to do
something. If I don't do,
I will forever stay one. And if I stays
forever one,
this condition will always be true. And
if it is always true,
that line of code will run run, run,
run, run run at 11.
This is where
something like increment or decrement,
your wish, comes in. And I say
this is the line that I use
I want to execute.
And I go ahead and write this line.
Now, what happens is see what will
happen. I'll tell you how it happens.
Oh,
10 times, exactly 10 times driver code
printed. What happened was
first, initialization, I equal to one.
First time,
I is one.
I less than 10? Yes. Goes,
prints. Printed, comes back to this
line.
I gets
two. Next, goes here.
Two less than equal to 10? Yes. Goes
here. Prints.
Goes again here.
I equal to three. After here, goes here.
Three less than equal to 10? Yes.
Prints.
Then goes here.
I equal to equal to four.
Imagine this is five for an example, so
that I can explain. I equal to four.
Prints. Goes again here.
I becomes five.
Prints.
Goes here. I becomes five. Checks.
Prints. Goes again here.
I becomes six.
The moment I becomes six, six less than
equal to five?
No, no.
Stop.
So, it will get executed five times. But
if you try to print the value of I,
imagine you want to print the value of
I. Something very important to notice.
If you print it like this,
it will not be able to find I. Why?
Because the scope of the I, the I was
declared inside this.
So, the scope,
wherever you declare I, the scope is
limited to that. So,
the other way you can do is
you can say I, and you can write
something like this. So, you declared
the I here, and then you have
initialized it here. So, if you print I
over here, see what happens. So, I print
I,
the last value of I is six, where it got
truncated. You can run the for loop in
the reverse order as well. Something
like, hey, maybe start from five.
Maybe go on till
and maybe decrease it.
So, if you do this, and if you print the
value of I, you can see the value of I.
Oh, sorry, my bad.
You want to print the value of I?
Maybe go like this. Oh, sorry, maybe
like this and yeah.
Let's see what you got.
See the value of I. Five for the first,
and fourth, and third, and second, and
first, and zero. Got it?
So, you can write the for loop as you
wish to. Is it mandatory that you reduce
by two? No.
I want to run this for five times. How I
run it for five times is my choice. I
can be like, one,
I can be like, I need for five times, I
will go till 25. I will do
I into or maybe I plus five.
My choice. I can go like one, six, 11,
16, 21. My choice. That's my choice. No
one is here to stay. How I run doesn't
matter. How many times I run is what
matters. This condition depends on you.
What you need to make sure is, if you
want it for five, if you want it for 10,
if you want it for 20, make sure the
condition is written in such a way that
it runs for that many number of times.
That is the core concept of for loops.
Do we have nested for loops? Similar to
if? Yes, we do have. And the nested for
loops is something which I'll be
teaching you while printing patterns. As
of now, this is what you need to know.
Can we write if conditions inside the
for loop? Yes, you can go ahead and
write if. Any line of code can be
written inside any for or any while
loop. So, this is how you write
a for loop. Now
I want to convert this exact similar for
loop. I'll just comment it out. I want
to convert this exact similar for loop
into a while loop.
So the while loop does the same thing.
The task is same. Whenever I attach
something like loop, the task remains
same. Executing some lines of code for
some number of times. We do the same
thing. I need here.
The only difference is
the syntax changes. While executes like
this. Whatever is the condition,
whatever is the condition will go here.
And whatever is the increment goes at
the end. Goes at the last line.
Whatever is the increment goes at the
last line. Okay? And the initialization
goes over here.
First time initialization happens. While
says 1 is lesser than equal to 5. Fine.
Go ahead and do see out of driver.
And if you want to print I's value, you
can also check it out. So if I go ahead
and do end L,
you will see the value. See?
Perfect. So what happens? Check, print,
increase, check, print, increase.
First check, goes inside, increases,
comes back, checks, prints, increases.
Very simple. This is how a while loop
executes. So this is about while loop.
Now while has one more concept. And that
concept is do while loop. Okay. Now what
does do while mean? So can I say if I
keep I equal to 2 and I keep something
like this, will it execute? The answer
to that is
no. Because I is 2, the condition is
false, never executes, goes to this,
ends the program. So do while says
you you don't know the condition because
when you are writing code in industry or
maybe you are solving a problem, you a
lot of times the condition might be user
dependent or you might have such use
cases.
So,
you always want one thing to happen,
that is you want your line of code to be
executed minimum for one time. Minimum
for one time.
That is one That is when you say, "Okay,
we want it to be executed for minimum of
one time. I will write it something like
do
and then I'll put this condition
for over here
at the end and then I'll be doing the
same thing.
I'll be doing the same thing. So, what
will happen is even if the while even if
the INDI is defined as two and the
condition doesn't executes because it
doesn't allows me. And then you end it
with a semicolon. Even if the condition
doesn't allows me, do says, "Do it for
the first."
Go ahead, do it for the first, then
increment, then check, then do. So, if
you see I equal to two, see what will
Striver two gets printed.
And then if you see the value of I at
the end of the while loop, let's print
what will happen.
The value of I was two.
You printed Striver. I increased to
three
and three was lesser than equal to one
and it got ex-
ended. But do will make sure the first
time it gets executed irrespective of
what condition you are given. So, the
this is the basic like you can define it
here, you can define it before this,
that is your choice. But this is the
basic of for and while loops. So, I can
say this is the basic of for and while
loops. Eventually, when we solve
these amazing set of patterns, the
concept of the for and while loops will
get more and more into your head and
you'll be very strong in logical
thinking and eventually you can apply
for loops in maths, recursion and all
the other problems, okay? What's the
next thing? Functions, pass by reference
and pass by value. Functions is very,
very important because we'll be using
functions throughout Yes, throughout to
solve any problems, we will be writing
functions. So, please make sure you
understand functions in a proper depth.
So, let's start with functions. What are
functions? Functions are a set of code
which performs something for you. Now,
if I want someone to do something for
me, like for an example, if I want to
order food, I can say I can deliver food
from a food delivery app and that will
bring me in food. So, you can say
functions are similar. You want it to do
something, you'll give it or maybe
something and it will do that for you.
That is the role of a function. Why are
functions used? Functions are used to
modularize code. Now, a lot of times
you'll be having hundreds and hundreds
of lines of code and it's it becomes
very clumsy. So, in order to modularize
because every portion of the code will
be doing something. So, that something
will be
put into a function, okay? Functions are
used to increase readability. Now,
imagine you are writing code and you
have like 1,000 lines of code.
You know you know what every line is
doing, but if someone from outside is
reading your code, you might not
understand. So, what you do is every
step you put it into a function. Name
the function in such a way that it is
understandable what it is doing. Got it?
And functions are used to same are used
to use the same code multiple time. So,
if you are performing same like if you
are using the same set of code again and
again, it's not good to write the same
code again and again. So, you can put
them into functions and use the
function, okay? So, I'll be showing you
all these things.
So, there are basically
So, there are a lot of kind of
functions, but usually we do use like
four kind of functions. One is the void
function, the other one is the return
function, the other one is where we
carry a lot of parameters. The other one
is where we do not carry any parameter.
Okay? So, non-parameterized functions.
So, let's uh talk about the first one,
void function.
The void function is something which
does not returns anything. Very
important. It doesn't returns anything.
So, imagine imagine
I'm saying print your name.
You know that is easy. You'll come
across and say, "Hey, see out."
Hey, stream out.
Printed.
So, you know one thing. If I'm saying,
"Hey, stream out."
That is something which I know. But if
someone is coming from outside and is
reading this, like, "What does see out
mean?" I don't know.
I don't know what see out means. This is
where readability comes in. If I do not
know C++, I will not be knowing what see
out means. That is where we say, "Okay.
Let me write a function." So, what
function I'll write is I'll say, "Okay,
void."
That is the keyword. It means it will do
something, but it will not give me
something. It will not give me
something. And then I'll write the
function name. I have to print the
names.
So, I'll just write print name.
And in that, I'll put this.
So, it did not return me anything. It's
a void. It will never return you
anything. And this is the function name,
and this is a non-parameter. It will not
carry any parameter. Whenever you
enclose it within parentheses and there
is nothing inside it, it doesn't carries
a parameter.
So, it does this. Now, over here, if you
just run this, this will not be
executing this function because this is
outside the main. You know the skeleton
of the code is executing anything that
is inside the int main, and the function
is outside. So, what do you do is you
say, "Print the name." And you execute
this. Now, what will happen is int main
will
print the name will happen, and then it
will go across and execute the line of
code.
See, hey Striver, executed. Now imagine
I say
take an input and print the name.
So you'll be like, okay, this is the
line of
maybe I'll take int name
and I'll say cin name.
And now I want to print this name. I
want to say, hey this name. And this
name might be Raj.
So if I say just print name, what will
happen? See, it'll still print hey
Striver. I want you to print hey Raj.
This is where something like a
parameterized void function comes in. I
know I have to take this name. Maybe
I'll pass this name.
So I'm saying print the name, take this
name.
Print name will say, okay, please give
me this. What Oh, by the way, string.
What is the data type of this name? It
says string. I'm passing the name, but
it gives you red. Why?
Because this guy is not taking any
parameters. But I'm giving it name. I'll
say, okay, what are you giving me?
You're giving me a string. I'll take the
string.
I'll take the string. When I've taken
the string, now I'll say, hey
can I say name?
See what will happen.
This function took this name and
printed. Now this moment when you say
Raj, see what happened.
Hey Raj. If you say
Striver,
it will say, hey Striver. If you say
Aman,
it will say, hey Aman.
Simple. This function, what is the
function of this function? Takes a name
and prints a name.
Very simple. It can take any name. So
you can maybe use it again. See, string
name two. And you can maybe take name
two. And you can say print name. See,
reusability of codes.
I'm using the code again and again. And
I can say, okay, Aman and then Raj. And
then maybe over here let's give an end
line so that every time it sees hey, you
like see what happens. Hey Aman, hey
Raj. Now, had you written this line,
you'd have written it again and again
and again. But this is where reusability
of code comes in. Now, this is not under
like you can maybe put it under for
loop, that is okay. But if there there
will be cases where you cannot use for
loops, but you have to use shuttle lines
of code again again at different
different places. That is where
something like a function comes. So, I
can call this as a void function and as
well as a parameter phrase function. So,
you have understood void, you have
understood parameterized, you have
understood non-parameterized. Okay. Now,
the next question that we will do is
take two numbers and print its sum. So,
what I'll do is I'll take two numbers.
The two numbers are on the input. So,
let's do this. I need num one,
num two. Let's take the two numbers,
num one and num two.
Now, I'll say see out of num one plus
num two. Or maybe you can do it
something like I need num three equal to
num one plus num two.
I can say let's print num three.
Perfect.
What will happen?
5 + 6 11 will be printed. Imagine this
addition operation you have to do it
multiple times. Imagine you're writing a
program for calculator. A lot of times
addition operator will be done. Can you
always just keep on writing plus plus
plus plus? No. That's when you have to
modularize the code and make it
readable. So, one thing you can do is
like
you can say, okay. What is this doing?
I'm giving two numbers and I'm saying
sum. We will always have two numbers to
take.
So, if you're trying to write a return
function, it will always be like integer
sum. Again, the name of the function can
be anything. It always takes two
numbers. So, there can be two
parameters. They can be any number of
parameters.
Multiple data types.
You can have something like char c as
well. That is okay.
num2
This is num3
equal to num1 plus num2.
And you can say return
num3. And over here what you can say is
I've taken the inputs.
And I can say the result will be I'll
say the sum guy to take num1
and to take num2. So the sum guy is
called. What happens? Let's understand
the line of executions.
So what happens? Let's understand the
execution.
So the main says, okay, num1 num2.
Take it as input, five and six. Five
goes to num1. Six goes to num2.
And then I call sum.
This is where the program stops. The
program stops at the line 21. Program
stops at line 21. And now it goes to
line 13. At 13
it is taking num1 which is five. It is
taking num2 which is six. So five and
six are passed over here. And it states
5 + 6.
And then num3 takes 5 + 6 which is 11.
And it says, return. Return the value.
So it returns 11. And this function Now
this function
gives you 11. Because this function was
called. This function gave you 11. And
that 11 goes and gets stored into res.
And then the line 21 which was stopped
will be executed. And then this line 22
will be performed. What is the value of
res now?
It is 11. So it gets printed. So
whenever you're calling a function,
first the function will be executed.
Whatever value the function gives, if it
is a return, that will be stored here.
Then the remaining lines will be
executed. On a function call, the flow
will go to the function. The flow will
go to the function. Got it?
This is what you call as a return
function. This will return something.
You could have done it as a void
function, void parameter space, and you
could have done see out now. That is
also okay. In that case, you don't have
to do this, and you don't have to do
this.
Different ways of writing code. A lot of
people write code in different ways. You
can write it as you wish. My main idea
is to teach you what are functions, what
different kind of functions you can
have. Now, remember one thing. If you
are writing as this and this
This can be anything. This can be an
integer, can be a double, can be a long
long, can be a string, can be an array,
can be a vector, can be a list, can be
anything. Can be anything. And you will
see eventually in the DSA playlist, we
will be writing functions where we'll be
returning vectors, arrays, 2D arrays.
There'll be a lot of things returned
from here. And we will learn throughout
the course. So, please make sure you
watch all the videos of this playlist
because I'm going to go in super depth.
Since we're talking about functions,
let's take these couple of numbers
again. And there are a lot of internal
functions. Remember, at the start I said
there is something as math.h.
So, there is an inbuilt function which
says, "Give me minimum." And if you
write min and you give them num one, num
two, and then you
print minimum, see what will happen.
The five is the minimum. Similarly,
there's max as well. And there are a lot
of inbuilt functions as well. Now, these
functions are similarly written. So, if
you have to write a max function, how
will you write? It'll be very simple.
It'll be like num one,
num two. And I know if I'm looking for
max, if num one conditional statement
greater than num two, I can say that
my max is num one. So, right? Or else I
can say is my max is num two. Now, there
is something
you cannot name the function with the
same name. So, make it max max, okay?
So, because
inbuilt max function exists, so you have
to give the function such a name that
the inbuilt
there is no such inbuilt functions.
There cannot be repetition of function
names. Okay. So, max now, will it work?
It should because
data type returns returns returns.
Let's see.
Will it work?
It does return. Does return. Okay. Now,
for an example, let's omit this line.
For an example, just for an instance,
let's omit this line.
This is an integer. This has a return
statement.
Will it work?
No, it didn't.
It did throw some random value. Why did
this happen?
Can you please tell me why did this
happen? The reason this happened was
let's understand one thing over here.
What did I say? I said number one
greater than equal to number two. So,
five
was greater than equal to six?
No. So, there was no if.
Since this if did not execute itself, by
the way, since there is one line, you
can always write it without braces.
Since this if
was not executed because I was stating
is five greater than equal to six, and
that was false. So, the if
never got executed. And since the if did
not get executed, the return line was
not executed. And since the return line
was not executed, this function was
looking for a
return line. It was looking for a return
line. And it did not find one.
Thereby,
it did give you like garbage stuff. So,
the program did not compile properly.
It's very important that if you are
writing an int data type stating that it
will always have a return, you make sure
you write a return.
You make sure you write a return.
That is very very important. Every
function which with a return data type
must have a return one.
Right? Make sure you do that. So, we did
learn about functions, but in the
bracket it is written pass by reference
and value. Let's understand what that
means. So, let's just take a number just
in order to understand
and do something. And we write a
function do something and pass the
number.
Okay. And we go over here and write
void. You know this is a function. So,
write do something.
And
to take this number
and maybe print it.
And go ahead change this number, let's
say add five to it. Again, print it.
And maybe again
add a five to it and again print it.
So, what will be the expected value?
I'm sending 10. So, 10 will be printed.
Then plus five 15, then 20. So, ideally
it should be 10, 15, 20. It is. But
what did I say about the execution? How
does the execution works? So, it is like
the first line is executed. Then it
calls it. So, it goes here. This is
executed. This is executed. This is then
this, then this and then the line 21,
then the 22, then
ends at 23.
So, ideally if I printed here
what should happen?
Ideally, according to your number was 10
it went here.
10, 15, 20
finished 21.
At 21 it should be again 20 because the
last value was 20. So, it should be 20,
right? Let's do.
We run this.
10, 15, 20 20 till here. But the moment
it came to the line 21, the value was
10 again. Why?
This is what we call as
pass by value. What happens is when you
call functions
and you pass
number
it goes by value. A copy goes.
Then the original number did not go. The
original number did not go. This
original number must be somewhere. Must
be somewhere in the memory.
That original memory did not go. What it
created was it said, "You are 10. Let me
create a copy. Send that copy. I'm not
sending original. I'm not sending
origin."
This guy
took the original. Took the original. He
said, "You are 10. Copy. Copy."
Take the copy and give it to the
function. And the function took the
copy. Did everything with the copy. Did
everything with the copy. They changed.
They modified the copy. So, since they
modified the copy, the original value
still stayed the same. This is what we
call as pass by value. Okay? This does
work with everything. Like, let's assign
string.
String S equal to Raj. And imagine you
pass the string S. And let's comment
this. And let's say string S again.
And over here, assume you say S zero
equal to instead of Raj I say Taj. T.
And I print the string S. And over here
also I print the string S. So, ideally
over here, if I'm changing S zero to T,
Raj will become Taj.
Right? And then when it comes back, S is
again printed. So,
what should happen?
Yes. First, it got changed. But since I
did not pass the original, I passed the
copy. Since I passed the copy, what
happened was
only the copy got changed and the
original still stayed the same. This is
what we call as pass by value. Now,
there's something as pass by reference.
What is this pass by reference?
I don't want to pass a copy.
I want my function to make changes on
the original one. That's when you just
attach
and do it. If you attach an and do it,
it takes the address. It takes the
address.
So, what are we sending over here?
It takes the original and sends it. So,
this string, whenever you say S,
it actually is dealing with the
original.
Let's now compile and see. So, if you
compile and see, you see
it changed here, and the same prevailed
over here. This is what you call as pass
by reference.
Understood? If you're passing like this
and sign will say that, "Okay, get it
from the address. Get it from the
address. Get the original value." Okay?
Now, this pass by reference can be
written in a lot of other ways, but I
personally feel the other ways are very,
very confusing. The easiest way is just
attach
a and sign, and that will make sure that
it is passed by reference. The original
value is passed. So, if you want to pass
the integer, similarly, you can do
integer num equal to 10, and you can
pass the num here, and let's bring the
num here, and again take INT. Again,
this pass the num here, and you can go
ahead and say, "Let's do the same thing.
See out of
num and L."
And over here, you can say num plus
equal to five. Again, you can say
see out of num and L. Again, you can say
num plus equal to five, and again, you
can say see out num and L. So, let's do.
So, if I run this, what should happen?
See?
Value got updated in the function three
times, and then still the same value
prevailed. Very simple. Now,
uh
thing that you have to keep in the mind.
Imagine you're declaring the array. So,
do you remember declaring the array?
Till now you were declaring the array
like five and imagine there are like
five values, 10, 7, 12, 30.
Till now, all these values you were kind
of taking like C and array of zero, C
and array of one, C and array of two, C
and array of three, C and array of four.
This is how you took and eventually you
were printing it array of zero, array of
one, and going on array of
two
and so on. You just printed it like
this, right? So, if you run this, you
saw all the values were getting printed
like in front of end L
in order to get a clarity. T.
Oh, here also you can put a end L. Okay.
So, if you just put an end L and run, so
yeah, the first three values are
printed. But, is this a good way?
Because there might be 500 numbers.
What did you learn? Looping array. Let's
combine them. Yes. I mean, what are you
thinking? Zero, one, two, three, four.
Can I write something like this?
Zero.
I I know I have to go till four.
Okay. I know I have to do this.
And if I know this,
can I say C and
array of I?
Can I do this?
Can I do this C and array of I?
What will happen? What's the first value
of I? Zero.
So, zero. Array of zero will get in. So,
five will get in.
Then, what's the value of I? One. So, 10
will get in array of one. Right? And
then what's the value of I? So, if you
try to print the value of I, if you
remember for loops,
Sorry, my bad.
See what will happen.
The value of I is zero. So, array of
zero is taken. Next, the value of I is
one. Array of one is taken. Next, the
value of I is two. So, array of two is
taken. And similarly, it takes
everything.
Perfect.
If you want to print it, quite simple.
Same way,
run a for loop.
You want to print everything, array
zero, array one.
Why do you want to write everything
again and again? Just write see out.
Give like this.
Maybe put a space.
And just see.
Everything got printed.
So, I combined array, loops, and
everything. Now,
a question comes up. Pass by reference.
I said include and to everything, but
this doesn't works for arrays. Arrays
are generically passed by reference. So,
if you write this,
this is a how you pass an array. So,
imagine this is the array I took as an
input, and I said do something. And I
said, "Can you please take this array
and maybe the size of the array? And the
size of the array is
five.
So, you can go ahead and maybe declare
it in a better way.
This.
Yeah, that's a better way. And maybe you
can loop till n minus one, or you can
loop till n. That is your choice.
You can do whatever you wish to. You can
loop till n minus one because last index
is n minus one, or you can write lesser
than. Both the conditions are meaning
the exact same thing. So, over here,
I'll take everything.
Now, what I'll do is I will go across to
every value of Maybe to just understand
array of zero, I will go ahead and add
plus equal to maybe 100 to it. And over
here, I'll print array of
uh
value inside function, okay?
And I'll say array of zero, please get
printed. Okay? And I'll say value inside
int main
after the function.
Okay?
Value inside int main.
Let's see
if that got added. Do you see this?
It stays 105. I did not pass it with
reference, but array
always goes with reference. So, please
keep this in mind. If you're passing an
array, it will always always go with
reference. But apart from that, vector,
maps, list, everything you have to pass
that and sign to make sure that it is
passed by reference. Got this?
So, whatever you do over here with the
arrays, that will be definitely modified
throughout.
So, with this we learn functions passed
by reference and value.
Time complexity is the next one which
I'll be covering in the next video
because time complexity in itself is a
very very vast topic and I want you to
understand this in proper depth with a
lot of examples. Why? Because this is
going to be the most important topics.
If you go for interviews, they'll be
like, "Do it in the least time
complexity." So, we'll be doing that in
the next one. And if you want to know
more about C++ you can definitely watch
out the C++ STL video. So, if you have
seen the video till here, I think you
should definitely hit that like button.
And if you've understood everything,
please do consider subscribing to us
because I was going through our channel
statistics. Nearly 50% of the users who
watch these kind of videos do not hit
that subscribe button. I know these are
educational videos, but if if you just
click that subscribe button, that does
motivate me to make such kind of videos.
And yes, this is going to be a
full-fledged playlist on data structures
and algorithms. So, do stay tuned.
Follow me on Twitter, Instagram,
LinkedIn so that you stay updated about
this particular playlist and make sure
you watch all the videos in this
playlist. In case you haven't checked
out other resources, you can definitely
check out by diving deep into the
playlist section of this particular
channel. And you can also go through our
Take You Forward website. With this I'll
be wrapping up this video. Let's meet in
some other video. Till then, bye-bye.
Take care. Whenever your heart is
broken,
don't ever forget you're golden.
I will find the light in you.